American Montessori Society Records 2006.0230
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Series VIII: AMI/AMS Correspondence ( 1963-1966 ) includes correspondence between AMI and AMS that had nothing to do with Nancy McCormick Rambusch or was written after she resigned as president of AMS in 1963. The series serves as a supplement to Series VII, Subseries A in chronicling the relationship between the two groups and showing the various difficulties that existed between the organizations. Some were financial; others involved AMI's reluctance to recognize AMS teacher training and issue diplomas and credentials to those trained under AMS auspices.
Series IX: Teaching Materials and Pedagogical Resouces ( undated, 1962-1967 ) includes a glossary compiled in 1962 by Nancy McCormick Rambusch, Reginald C. Orem, and George L. Stevens; lesson plans and outlines; explanations of Montessori activities and apparatus; and the Teacher's Manual for the 1966-1967 Montessori Teacher Training Program, some of which was prepared by Rambusch.
Series X: Historical Articles and Papers ( undated, 1915-1998 ) includes writings on Maria Montessori and the Montessori method and movement from a historical perspective. Subseries A features writings by Maria Montessori, including Dr. Montessori's Own Handbook, and historical and biographical articles about her. There are clippings and letters, some on fading thermofaxes, and the words and music for "Hymn for Maria Montessori" by Katy Paraskevopulu. Subseries B contains articles on the Montessori movement that describe its evolution and what it actually is. They are concerned with the movement in general, not specific aspects of research. Most date from the early- and mid-1960s when the movement was gaining momentum; many, therefore, are from Catholic publications and mention Nancy McCormick Rambusch (duplicates of some of these articles will be found in Series VII, Subseries C). Subseries C contains typed copies of transcripts of lectures given in 1915 by Maria Montessori in San Francisco, San Diego, and Los Angeles. There is also a manuscript by Buckenmeyer on Maria Montessori based on conversations in 1969 with Edna Andriano, who cared for Mario Montessori when he was a child. Subseries D includes articles and correspondence on the history of Montessori by the educator Sol Cohen. Subseries E features materials on Montessori donated by Ray Franchi after the death of his wife, Lucille, a Montessori educator. Typescripts and newspaper clippings from the San Francisco Call & Post of the texts of Maria Montessori's 1915 lectures are included, as is a copy of Maria Montessori: A Centenary Anthology. In addition, there is a letter written by Lucille Franchi to Hillary Clinton about children's education; "Letters to Susan, A Discouraged Teacher," in which Franchi discusses aspects of the Montessori method; and an imaginary conversation between Maria Montessori and Gandhi composed by Ray Franchi. Subseries F contains excerpts of notes taken by E. M. Standing during lectures given by Maria Montessori in 1921. Subseries G contains notebooks, correspondence and professional records of Lakshmi A. Kripalani who was trained by Maria Montessori in 1946 in Karachi, India (now Pakistan) before working in Montessori schools in New Jersey. Subseries H contains the notebooks of Edith Cary who trainined under Maria Montessori in London, England, before opening the first Montessori school in Mansfield, Connecticut (Oak Grove). Subseries I holds the training materials created by Mildred W. Harford (undated). Subseries J contains the personal notes of Hannah MacLaren taken during Teacher Training in 1963 in California.
Series XI: Research ( undated, 1960s-circa 1970 ) contains writings concerning research on specific aspects of the Montessori system. Subseries A consists of papers and articles, mainly in typescript, reflecting the research of numerous scholars and educators. These were collected by the AMS office to serve as a resource for Montessori scholarship; some later appeared in publications by AMS or other organizations. They are arranged alphabetically by author's last name. Subseries B contains bibliographies of Montessori research, including an index card file (see Series VII Subseries C for a bibliography by Nancy McCormick Rambusch), and abstracts of articles and dissertations on Montessori.
Series XII: Consultation Program ( undated, 1965-1979 ) contains mainly administrative aspects and functions of AMS's Consultation Program (also known as the Visitation Program). Subseries A contains lists of AMS School Visitors, mainly from the 1960s and 1970s, the Consultation Services Handbook, annual reports to the Board of Directors, and correspondence and reports dealing with expenses and financial matters such as travelling reimbursements for consultants. Subseries B consists of correspondence about specific visits to participating schools. Procedural activities of the Consultation Program are discussed. There are reports to the Board of Directors (1965-1979) and public relations appeals describing the benefits of the Consultation Program in an effort to increase participation by AMS-affiliated schools. Subseries C, D, and E contain the files of three coordinators of the Consultation Program. There are many handwritten and typed notes and memos, usually but not always to or from the coordinators; sometimes the documents are copies of letters and other papers that a coordinator would naturally need to know about and maintain in her files. Routine administrative matters are discussed, as well as problems or issues with individuals within the program. Subseries F includes correspondence of individual consultants, usually to or from the coordinator or Cleo Monson, arranged alphabetically by last name of the consultant. The letters and memos generally address routine housekeeping matters such as expense reports and reimbursements.
Series XIII: Seminars and Conferences ( undated, 1963-1990 ) chronicles the seminars and conferences, both national and regional, conducted every year by AMS. Special meetings, such as the International Symposium in Athens (1979) and the 19th International Montessori Congress in Amsterdam (1979), are also covered. Not all the seminars held during 1963-1990 are included, but there is a list of all the seminars for these years at the beginning of the series, as well as registration lists for the conferences of 1963-1977 and brochures and other publicity for conferences between 1985 and 1990. For each seminar there are letters, memos, and other records dealing with exhibits and exhibitors, presenters, publicity, financial matters, and hotels and convention centers. For most seminars there are programs listing the presenters, speakers, and various activities. A large portion of the documents concern the types of routine financial transactions between convention centers and the organization, or participants and the organization, that typically occur during meetings of professional societies. There are also evaluation forms completed by the participants that provide impressions of the strengths and weaknesses of a particular conference and how successful or well-received it was.
Series XIV: AMS Publications ( undated, 1960-1999 ) includes issues of various journals and newsletters published by AMS, and also correspondence related to them. Each subseries is devoted to a specific publication. The publications themselves have been separated from the collection and are cataloged. There are gaps in every subseries, though the most complete is Subseries A, the American Montessori Society Bulletin, which also contains a list of published issues. Subseries C, D, and F reflect title changes for the same publication: in 1970 AMS News Notes became AMS Newsletter, which, later that same year, became AMS News. In 1980, however, a new American Montessori Society Newsletter began that had no relation to the old AMS Newsletter (the only difference in the later title was that the name of the organization was spelled out instead of abbreviated). In this collection, to avoid possible confusion, the AMS Newsletter has been designated o.s. (old series) while the American Montessori Society Newsletter has been designated n.s. (new series), though these distinctions were never used by the publications themselves. In Subseries I the Constructive Triangle, the AMS's official journal, is represented by only a few issues, but there is an index of articles and the text of several articles, mainly in typescript.
Series XV: Brochures, Pamphlets, Publicity and Press Releases ( undated ) provides a sampling of the literature generated by AMS over the years to advertise its mission and the Montessori method, and includes lists of AMS publications and materials. Included are compilations of this literature created by the AMS office in the form of seven scrapbooks: one consists of general materials; the other six are organized around specific topics.
Series XVI: Correspondence and Publicity for AMS Films ( undated, 1973 ) consists of correspondence, scripts, and publicity about several film projects that AMS was involved in, including Montessori: An Education for Life and the AMS Slide/Film Contest of 1973.
Series XVII: Montessori and AMS-affiliated Schools ( undated, 1962-1976 ) contains records relating to AMS-affiliated schools in general and also specific schools. Some of the included items are lists of affiliates, various bylaws, overviews of and statistical data on affiliates, questionnaire, tuition, and application forms, information on how to start an affiliated school, brochures, publicity, mailings, and floor plans from specific schools, admissions policies, and affiliate membership appeals. Folders for specific schools are arranged alphabetically by title.
Series XVIII: Child Development Associate Consortium ( undated, circa 1972-1976 ) The AMS eventually became a member of the Child Development Associate Consortium ( CDAC), a private, nonprofit organization consisting of numerous societies directly involved in child development and early childhood education. The documents in this series consist of brochures and correspondence about CDAC and AMS's membership in it, as well as minutes from CDAC's Board of Directors' meetings and information on credentials and certification, including a 1974 paper by CDAC.
Series XIX: Comite Hispano Montessori ( undated, circa 1975-1991 ) The Comite Hispano Montessori is a nonprofit Montessori organization providing a communication network and services for educators in Spanish-speaking communities in the United States, Mexico, the Caribbean, and Central and South America. The series contains correspondence, publicity, and directories of the Comite Hispano Montessori, consultation reports on affiliate schools, and teachers' résumés. Clippings, correspondence, and a financial report for a seminar in June 1979 held in Monterrey, Mexico, are also included.
Series XX: Educational Groups and Organizations ( undated ) contains correspondence, brochures, and other literature on various groups relevant to AMS's interests, such as educational toy companies, day-care and home-schooling organizations, and Waldorf Institutes. Included is the manual Home Study Course in Modern Montessori Teaching by the School of Modern Montessori. Of interest are the materials on the Waldorf Institutes, especially the Rudolf Steiner School in New York, which consist of pamphlets explaining the history and content of anthroposophy, literature on schools, events, and curricula, and an article in Holistic Education 3:4 (Winter 1990) that features a comparison of the Waldorf and Montessori methods in a discussion among educators from both traditions.
Series XXI: Non-AMS Publications ( undated ) includes writings from organizations other than AMS on Montessorian topics, including an article on teaching music by the Montessori method in Piano Quarterly 58 (Winter 1996-97). Publications by AMI are also located here, and include Mario Montessori's "yellow paper" outlining his philosophical disagreements with the AMS (see Series VII, Subseries A for the typescript version), a few issues of AMI's journal Communications, an index to articles in Communications, and materials from the 13th International Montessori Congress, held in April 1964 in Amsterdam.
Series XXII: Sound Recordings ( undated, 1969-2005 ) includes audiocassettes, reel-to-reel audiotapes, and LP phonograph records. The cassettes and tapes consist of lectures, speeches, presentations, and workshops, mainly from various AMS seminars. Subseries A consists of approximately 2787 audiocassettes dating from the 1970s through 2003. Nancy McCormick Rambusch and other prominent Montessorians are featured on many of the cassettes. Subseries B includes 58 audiotapes (reel-to-reel) from the early 1960s and the AMS Chicago Seminar of June 1969. The most recent tape dates from 1970. Subseries C contains master and duplicate recordings of Folk Tunes and Music of the Masters Adapted for the Classroom by Elsie Braun Barnett. Subseries D contains a CD version of the Barnett phonorecord.
Series XXIII: Videocassettes and Films ( undated, 1970-1987 ) includes Subseries A which consists of videocassettes from the 1980s, including an interview by Bob Motley of Nancy McCormick Rambusch and Cleo Monson at the AMS Seminar in Wilmington, Delaware, in November 1986, for which a transcript is included. Subseries B contains numerous films, mostly by AMS and about aspects of the Montessori method.
Series XXIV: Photographs and Slides ( undated, 1907-1980 ) contains Subseries A consisting of photographs that depict the numerous activities and phases of AMS throughout its history, and include photographs of Nancy McCormick Rambusch and many other individuals whose names appear frequently throughout this collection. Seminars, social events such as Christmas parties and Cleo Monson's retirement festivities in 1978, proofs for various publications, and Montessori schools, classrooms, and students are well represented. Subseries B features slides illustrating Montessori teaching activities and events, such as the Montessori Centennial Celebration in 1970.
Series XXV: Unprocessed additions ( undated, 1955-2007 ) includes materials that have been recently added to the collection but remain unprocessed.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
American Montessori Society newsletter Dodd Periodicals
American Montessori Society ... fall regional conference: [program] Dodd Periodicals
American Montessori Society bulletin Dodd Periodicals
AMS news Dodd Periodicals
Annual national conference: [program] Dodd Periodicals
Annual report to the membership Dodd Periodicals
L’Association "Centre Nascita Montessori" a´ Rome: une ide´e, une histoire de`s 1947 jusqu’a` aujourd’hui Dodd A8212
Constructive triangle Dodd Periodicals
Learning how to learn: an American approach to Montessori Dodd A8294
M the folios Dodd Periodicals
M: the magazine for Montessori families Dodd Periodicals
Il materiale Montessori in cataloghi editi a New York, Londra, Bucarest, Berlino, Gonzaga tra gli anni dieci e trenta Dodd C9465
Montessori: a therapeutic tool for the mentally retarded child Dodd XA I.33 no.36
Montessori Birth Centre Association in Rome Dodd A8211
Montessori community directory Dodd Periodicals
Montessori community resource Dodd Periodicals
Montessori elementary material Dodd A8296
Montessori life Dodd Periodicals
Montessori method: scientific pedagogy as applied to child education in The Children’s Houses with additions and revisions by the author Dodd A8293
Nascita del "segno": un’esperienza con bambini piccoli condotta da Luisa Gardini Stocchi Dodd C9466
National Montessori reporter Dodd Periodicals
National seminar: [program] Dodd Periodicals
News notes Dodd Periodicals
Public school Montessorian Dodd Periodicals Oversize
Il quaderno Montessori Dodd Periodicals
Regional seminar: [program] Dodd Periodicals
Spontaneous activity in education Dodd A8295
Teaching opportunities in AMS-member schools Dodd A8297
Verifiche: periodico di cultura e di politica dell’educazione Dodd Periodicals
Whitby School, 30 Years Dodd
Folk Tunes and Music of the Masters 2006-0230.cd1
Custodial History
The collection was acquired in 1997 by Special Collections, Milbank Memorial Library, Columbia Teachers College, under the supervision of David Ment, Associate Director and Head, Special Collections, and Bette Weneck, Manuscript Curator, Special Collections.
Acquisition Information
The collection was transferred in 2006 to the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center by the American Montessori Society, in coordination with Special Collections at Columbia Teachers College. Ongoing donations from AMS and individuals are integrated regularly.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to professional and educationally focused organizations. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
American Montessori Society.; Monson, Cleo.; Montessori, Maria.; National Center for Montessori Education (U.S.).; Rambusch, Nancy McCormick.; Administrative records; Audio visual materials; Audiocassettes; Bylaws; Correspondence; Education; Financial Records; Fliers [printed matter]; Greenwich (Conn.); Interviews; Manuscripts (document genre); Minutes (administrative records); Montessori method of education; Moving images; Newsletters; Notes; Oral histories (document genres); Photocopies; Photographs; Publications; School Records; Sound recordings; Typescripts; United States; Videocassettes; Women educators
- Series I: Minutes, 1963-1995
  - 1963 June (Box 44:, Folder 1)
  - 1964 November (Box 44:, Folder 2)
  - 1964 October - 1968 June (Box 44:, Folder 3)
  - 1968 October - 1972 June (Box 44:, Folder 4)
  - 1972 October - 1976 June (Box 44:, Folder 5)
  - 1976 October - 1980 June (Box 45:, Folder 6)
  - 1980 October - 1984 June (Box 45:, Folder 7)
  - 1984 November (Box 45:, Folder 8)
  - 1985 April (Box 45:, Folder 9)
  - 1985 November (Box 45:, Folder 10)
  - 1986 April (Box 46:, Folder 11)
  - 1986 November (Box 46:, Folder 12)
  - 1987 April (Box 46:, Folder 13)
  - 1987 November (Box 46:, Folder 14)
  - 1988 April (Box 46:, Folder 15)
  - 1988 November (Box 47:, Folder 16)
  - 1989 November (Box 47:, Folder 17)
  - 1989 April (Box 47:, Folder 18)
  - 1990 November (Box 48:, Folder 19)
  - 1990 April (Box 48:, Folder 20)
  - 1991 [incomplete] (Box 48:, Folder 21)
  - 1992 January (Box 48:, Folder 22)
  - 1992 November (Box 48:, Folder 23)
  - 1993 Spring [incomplete] (Box 48:, Folder 24)
  - 1993 November (Box 48:, Folder 25)
  - 1994 April (Box 48:, Folder 26)
  - 1994 October (Box 48:, Folder 27)
  - 1995 May (Box 48:, Folder 28)
  - 1995 November (Box 48:, Folder 29)
- Series II: By-Laws and Amendments, circa 1960-1973
  - undated, circa 1960 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - 1962 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - 1963 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - 1964 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - 1965 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - 1967 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - 1971 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - 1972 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - 1973 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
- Series III: Administrative Files, undated, 1959-1978
  - Subseries A: Administrative Reports and Policy Statements, 1963, 1976
    - AMS Policy Statement, 1963 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - National Director's Report to the AMS Board of Directors, 1976 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Subseries B: AMS Management Guide before completion, undated
    - AMS Management Guide Before Completion, undated (Box 1:, Folder 3-6)
  - Subseries C: Educational Advisory Committee, undated
    - Educational Advisory Committee, undated (Box 2:, Folder 7)
  - Subseries D: Evaluation of Foreign Student Credentials, undated
    - Evaluation of Foreign Student Credentials, undated (Box 2:, Folder 8)
  - Subseries E: Visitor Exchange Program, undated
    - Visitor Exchange Program, undated (Box 2:, Folder 9)
  - Subseries F: AMS Regional Semniar on all day programs, 1973 April
    - Report on AMS Regional Seminar on All Day Programs, 1973 April (Box 2:, Folder 10)
  - Subseries G: Fundraising Drive, 1981
    - Fundraising Drive, 1981 (Box 2:, Folder 11-12)
  - Subseries H: Office Maintenance and Personnel Files, undated
    - AMS Physical Properties: Leases, Correspondence, Maintenance, undated (Box 2:, Folder 13)
    - Insurance for Teachers, undated (Box 2:, Folder 14)
- Series IV: Mailing Scrapbooks, 1974-1983
  - 1974-1975 (Box 3)
  - 1976-1977 (Box 4)
  - 1978-1979 (Box 5)
  - 1980-1981 (Box 6)
  - 1982-1983 (Box 7)
- Series V: Federal and State Agencies, 1962-1983
  - Pennsylvania Department of Education, General Correspondence, 1969-1980 (Box 7:, Folder 1)
  - Pennsylvania State Board of Private Academic Schools: Policy Changes Toward Montessori Schools, 1962-1983 (Box 8a:, Folder 2)
  - U.S. Dept. of Health, Education, and Welfare, 1968-1976 (Box 8a:, Folder 3)
- Series VI: Royall O'Brien Files, 1962
  - 1962 (Box 8a:, Folder 1)
- Series VII: Nancy McCormick Rambusch Files, undated, circa 1956-1994
  - Subseries A: General and Business Correspondence, 1955-1977
    - Association Montessori Internationale ( AMI), 1955-1959 (Box 8b:, Folder 1)
    - AMI, Affiliation, 1960 (Box 8b:, Folder 2a)
    - AMI, XIIth Congress, 1960 (Box 8b:, Folder 2b)
    - Whitby School, 1960 (Box 8b:, Folder 2c)
    - AMI, Affiliation, 1961 (Box 8b:, Folder 3a)
    - AMS, general, 1961 (Box 8b:, Folder 3b)
    - Whitby School, 1961 (Box 8b:, Folder 3c)
    - AMS, AMI, Whitby, 1962 January - May (Box 8b:, Folder 4a)
    - AMS, AMI, Whitby, 1962 June - December (Box 8b:, Folder 4b)
    - General and Business Correspondence, 1963-1977 (Box 9:, Folder 5)
  - Subseries B: Personal Correspondence and Papers, undated, 1951
    - Personal Correspondence and Papers, undated (Box 9:, Folder 6)
    - Wedding announcement (newsclipping from an unidentified newspaper) and photographs of Nancy McCormick Rambusch on her wedding day to Robert Rambusch on 2 June 1951, 1951 June 2 (Box 2012-0058_1)
  - Subseries C: Writings by and about Nancy McCormick Rambusch, undated, 1962-1981
    - Articles, Interviews and Reviews by and about Nancy McCormick Rambusch, undated (Box 9:, Folder 7)
    - "The American Response to Montessori: 1910-1919,", 1964 (Box 9:, Folder 8)
    - "Annotated Bibliography and Critique of Selected Montessori Works in English,", 1962 (Box 9:, Folder 9)
    - "At What Age Should Systematic Reading Instruction Begin,", undated (Box 9:, Folder 10)
    - "The Children's House Manual,", 1977 (Box 9:, Folder 11)
    - "Learning to Read: Discerning the Scriptures,", 1967 (Box 9:, Folder 12)
    - "Montessori Glossary,", 1962 (Box 9:, Folder 13)
    - "The New Generation of Montessori Schools,", 1981 (Box 9:, Folder 14)
    - "The System of Numeration,", 1963 (Box 9:, Folder 15)
  - Subseries D: Nancy McCormick Rambusch-Condolensces and Obituary, 1994
    - Condolences (Box 10:, Folder 16)
    - Press Clippings (Box 10:, Folder 17)
- Series VIII: AMI/AMS Correspondence, 1963-1966
  - 1963 (Box 10:, Folder 1)
  - 1964-1966 (Box 10:, Folder 2)
- Series IX: Teaching Materials and Pedagogical Resources, undated, 1962-1967
  - Montessori Exercises, Lesson Plans, and Nomenclature, undated (Box 10:, Folder 1)
  - "A Montessori Glossary,", 1962 (Box 10:, Folder 2)
  - Montessori Teacher Training Program--1966-1967 Teachers Manual, undated (Box 10:, Folder 3)
- Series X: Historical Articles and Papers, undated, 1915-
  - Subseries A: Historical and Biographical Writings Concerning Maria Montessori, undated
    - Articles and Other Writings By or About Maria Montessori, undated (Box 11:, Folder 1)
    - Dr. Montessori's Own Handbook, undated (Box 11:, Folder 2)